Guide to the Records of the American Institute of the City of New York for the Encouragement of Science and Invention 1808-1983 (Bulk 1828-1940) MS 17
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
American Institute of the City of New York for the Encouragement of Science and Invention Records
1808-1983 (Bulk 1828-1940)
MS 17
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
272.0 Linear feet (491 boxes and 508 bound volumes)
The records of the American Institute document over 175 years of fairs, programs, and activities of an organization committed to the promotion of American industry, agriculture, and science.
Provenance
Donation by The American Institute of the City of New York for the Encouragement of Science and Invention, 1947. Supplement, donation by The American Institute of Science and Technology of the City of New York, 1985.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to ten exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.) Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading Room for details.
Historical Note
The American Institute of the City of New York was founded on February 19, 1828, and was incorporated the next year. The Institute's Charter states its purpose as the "encouraging and promoting domestic industry in this State, and the United States, in Agriculture, Commerce, Manufacturing and the Arts, and any improvements made therein." It attempted to fulfill that task by two means: first, by organizing annual fairs at which prizes were awarded to outstanding artisans and inventors, and second, by actively promoting government policies that would encourage and protect domestic manufacturing, agriculture, and commerce.
In 1828, when the American Institute was founded, a tariff bill was before Congress and the American Institute, unlike similar organizations such as the Franklin Institute of Philadelphia, made no secret of its support of the new tariff. Advocates of the bill regarded it as essential for protecting American manufacturing from overseas competition, particularly from Great Britain. Throughout the 19th Century, the Institute promoted the idea of protectionism and government spending on infrastructure. The Institute also published numerous pamphlets on these subjects, including articles on protectionism and internal improvements in its magazine, Journal of the American Institute of the City of New York (later, Transactions of the American Institute of the City of New York). In the years before the Civil War, the Institute's annual fairs routinely opened with addresses and lectures on political economy.
The fairs were scheduled annually, though there were a handful of years when a fair was not held. The first fair was held in October 1828, eight months after the Institute's founding. Entrants were, in the early years of the Institute, mostly artisans and manufacturers from New York City, New York State and New Jersey, and occasionally from New England. The earliest fair represented in the collection, in 1831, had 346 entrants. Over the years, however, the fairs attracted more participants, and the 23rd Fair, held in 1850, had over 2,000 entrants. By this time, the fairs included exhibitors from all of the New England and Middle Atlantic States, and occasionally from the South and West.
The Institute itself was divided into four departments: Agriculture, Commerce, Manufacturing, and the Arts; upon joining, members were assigned to one of the departments. Since the Institute had given itself the broad mission of fostering manufacturing, agriculture, and commerce throughout the United States, and also included the Arts under its purview, exhibitors at the fairs demonstrated a wide range of skills. In addition to industrial and agricultural exhibits, the fairs included the fine and decorative arts, with exhibitions of painting and sculpture, as well as wax fruit and stuffed and mounted animals.
In the periods between fairs, inventors and businesses sent the Institute a wide variety of goods, including books, seeds, and plans or models of new or improved machinery, asking that the Institute test and evaluate the submissions. The Institute appointed experts, singly or in committees, to make the assessments and report their findings. The Institute also actively advocated a tariff on imported goods, reform of patent law, and a federal bankruptcy law. Another matter of particular importance to the Institute was the development of a domestic silk industry in the United States.
In the pre-Civil War era, the fairs reflected the transition from cottage industry to commercial manufacturing. Premiums were awarded to individual artisans for superior work in fabricating articles like pails or barrels; at the same time, however, the American Institute was as likely to award prizes to inventors who successfully mechanized the processes for making such articles, thus making the artisans obsolete. The Institute's fairs also provided a venue for public demonstrations of some of the most significant inventions of the 19th Century, including Morse's telegraph and Colt's revolvers.
A symbiotic relationship existed between the Institute and the winners of the Institute's premiums. As the American Institute awarded prizes, it became more visible, and prize winners took advantage of the Institute's prestige by featuring their awards in their advertising. As its endorsements grew in prestige, the Institute sometimes received correspondence from exhibitors who had received lesser awards, complaining that they deserved gold medals. In 1840, a scandal erupted when it was alleged that exhibitors were paying the Institute to upgrade silver medals to gold. Not a legal matter, the Institute survived the scandal with its reputation intact.
From the Institute's beginnings through the post-Civil War period, its fairs drew eminent exhibitors and were well attended by the public. At the opening of the 40th Annual Fair in 1871, Walt Whitman read a poem celebrating industrial progress, and, by extension, the fair and its sponsor. That same year, the Institute's president, E.G. Squier, proposed that the Institute acquire property from the city to construct a permanent "Palace of Industry" in New York. Although the permanent exhibition was never realized, the annual fairs continued, and remained a prominent fixture in the city's cultural calendar.
In 1892, however,the annual fair ran a deficit for the first time. The Institute attributed this to the depressed economy and to competition for exhibitors from the Chicago World's Fair. The board of the American Institute then cancelled the 1893 Annual Fair. The Institute seems at this time to have undergone a brief period of indecision about its future course. In 1896, and again in 1897, it held fairs, but neither was financially successful. The Board of Trustees concluded, in its 1897 Annual Report (dated January 20, 1898) that "the era of the fair as an advertising medium, as well as a popular resort, must be recorded as an amusement and business venture of the past."
Nevertheless, the Institute remained solvent, and its real estate and bond holdings generated income. The Institute's charter required it to hold Annual Fairs, so the Institute continued to hold annual shows of flowers and agricultural products. Unlike the fairs of the 19th Century, which lasted for up to two months, the "Grand Chrysanthemum Shows" were one or two day affairs.
The Institute seems to have chafed at its loss of importance and prestige. In 1914, the Board of Trustees of the American Institute appointed a committee to solicit advice from a variety of experts on how the Institute could "increase its usefulness." Suggestions ranged from arranging lecture series to holding concerts to producing motion pictures that detailed industrial processes. Aside from sponsoring occasional lectures, nothing seems to have come of these suggestions. By the 1920's, however, some Institute-sponsored lectures were broadcast on the radio, which served to raise the Institute's profile somewhat.
In 1924, the Institute once again tried to mount a fair that recalled its former success. An "Inventors' Exhibition" was held in 1924, and another in 1925. These fairs were considerably smaller than those held in the 19th Century, and were only week-long exhibitions, but appear to have been popular with the public and rewarding for exhibitors. Nevertheless, the series of Inventors' Exhibitions lost money and ended in 1927.
In the late 1920's the Institute realized that it would have to transform itself in order to survive. Its members increasingly realized that technological progress was no longer a novelty and mass production had ceased to be exceptional. Advertising created mass markets for new products and obviated the need for industrial exhibitions.
The Institute responded to the challenge by changing its approach. On the one hand, it tried, with some success, to associate itself with the fields of scientific research that were expanding in the post-World War I era. It hosted dinners for outstanding scientists from both academic and corporate institutions. It continued its lecture series and radio broadcasts, now emphasizing developments in disciplines such as chemistry, engineering, and electronics, rather than manufacturing or agriculture.
The strategy of sponsoring lectures by eminent scientists helped to boost the membership of the Institute by attracting a younger generation of members with academic backgrounds in the sciences. By the end of the 1920's, however, the American Institute's Board of Trustees began to regard the emphasis on science as unfaithful to the original mission of the Institute, which had included under its purview the arts and agriculture. The trustees also seem to have balked at the expense represented by the honoraria paid to lecturers and guest speakers at Institute functions. In 1930, the trustees determined to cancel the adult programs. This provoked a controversy within the ranks of the Institute, and at a tumultuous meeting in November 1930, most of the existing board was voted out and replaced by younger members of a more scientific bent. The adult programs continued throughout the 1930's and beyond. A merger with the New York Electrical Society, also in 1930, solidified the Institute's engagement with the scientific community.
The American Institute also transformed itself into an advocate for scientific education. To this end, the Institute courted a constituency of scientists of the future. In 1928, the Institute held its annual Children's Fair. The American Institute claimed that it developed the idea of the children's science fair that later became popular with schools and other organizations.
The Institute continued and expanded its educational activities for children. The children's science fairs remained popular throughout the 1930's and the Institute sponsored meetings, workshops and radio programs for children. Its membership drives garnered applications from individuals throughout the United States, and student science clubs sought affiliation with the American Institute. During the 1930's, the Institute developed relationships with two important corporate sponsors, Westinghouse and IBM. In 1939, the American Institute sponsored a children's exhibit in the Westinghouse pavilion at the 1939-1940 World's Fair. After the fair, Westinghouse and IBM also created an advanced scientific laboratory for the use of gifted students from New York City high schools. By the end of the decade, the Institute was creating children's publications including the bi-monthly magazine, Science Observer, that had subscribers nationwide.
The series of adult programs that the Institute sponsored ended in the early 1940's. Thereafter, until the early 1980's the Institute concerned itself primarily with producing science fairs for students in New York City schools. Prize-winners were awarded a small sum of money, usually not exceeding twenty dollars for a first-prize winner. The money for these awards appears to have been provided by the American Association for the Advancement of Science, with which the American Institute was by this time affiliated. The last entry for the American Institute in the Encyclopedia of Associations appears in the 1983 edition.
Scope and Content Note
The American Institute records document over 175 years of committment to the promotion of American industry, agriculture, and science. Although materials in the collection date from 1808-1983, the bulk of the material is from 1828-1940. The collection documents the administration of the organization as well as its efforts to promote American Institute objectives through annual fairs, publications, adult programs and lectures, children's science fairs, and a children's exhibit at the 1939 World's Fair. The shifting goals of the American Institute, from the promotion of agriculture to the encouragement of industrialization to the promotion of science and technology, reflect the history of technological progress in American society.
The pre-1920 annual fair material relates to the planning of the American Institute fairs as well as information on the judges, exhibitions, and awards presented. The post-1920 material includes correspondence, press releases, and planning information regarding the children's fairs and programs as well as adult lectures and workshops. The collection also includes various materials related to the design and operation of the American Institute's children's exhibit in the Westinghouse Pavilion of the 1939 World's Fair. The Administrative subseries for the pre-1920 and the post-1920 material contains bound volumes and correspondence, reports, membership records, and financial papers that detail executive decisions and the general operation of the organization. The collection also contains pamphlets, publications, scrapbooks, artifacts, and visual materials of the American Institute.
An item level index to the materials created by the American Institute is available at the Manuscript Department reference desk.
Arrangement
Original order within the folders, and the titles of the folders, have for the most part been retained. Upon transfer to the New-York Historical Society, a significant portion of the pre-1928 material was maintained in its original folder-level filing order. Most of this material was in tri-fold bundles. Folder titles appearing in quotation marks denote titles assigned by the American Institute. Titles appearing without quotation marks denote titles assigned for purposes of this arrangement. Folder titles do not necessarily include all the forms or genres of material found within the folders. For example, correspondence can be found in folders labeled Reports and Papers, as well as in those labeled Correspondence.
Folders are arranged chronologically. Researchers should note that some folders span several years and that some material might pre-date or post-date the date recorded in the title of the folder. Within each box, folders were placed according to the earliest date assigned by the American Institute's original folder title. If the American Institute did not date the folder, it was placed according to the earliest inclusive date.
The Records of the American Institute
Series 1: Annual Fair Years, 1808-1930
Series 2: Children's Fair Years, 1921-1983
Series 3: Scrapbooks, 1845-1941
Series 4: Pamphlets and Publications, 1829-1941, undated
Series 5: Visual Materials, 1925-1927, undated
Series 6: Artifacts, undated
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
Other material related to the American Institute includes American Institute publications, catalogues of fairs and exhibitions, catalogues of the American Institute library, and catalogues of the photographic salons. Consult Bobcat at http://www.bobcat.nyu.edu for specific information.
American Association for the Advancement of Science; American Institute of the City of New York. Fair; American Institute of the City of New York.--Periodicals; American Institute of the City of New York; Crystal Palace (New York, N.Y.); International Business Machines Corporation; Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1791-1872; New York Electrical Society; New York World's Fair (1939-1940); Westinghouse Electric & Manufacturing Company; Account books; Agriculture--United States; Annual reports; Associations, institutions, etc.--New York (State)--New York; Associations, institutions, etc.--United States; Bank Books; Clippings; Contracts; Correspondence; Education--New York (State)--New York; Ephemera; Insurance Policies; Inventions--United States; Invitations; Leases; Ledgers; Medals; Minutes; Pamphlets; Photographic prints; Press releases; Printing blocks; Protectionism--United States; Real property--New York (State)--New York; Receipts; Reports; Science clubs; Science--Study and teaching; Scrapbooks; Sericulture--United States; Tickets; United States--Commerce; Vouchers
- Series 1: Annual Fair Years, 1808-1930
  - Subseries 1: Annual Fairs, 1828-1926
    Scope and Contents note
    The material in this subseries relates to the annual fairs of the American Institute. It consists of foldered items as well as bound volumes. The foldered material is organized chronologically. Generally, the same types of records (Vouchers, Judges Reports, and Reports of Managers, etc.) recur for each fair. The titles of the folders were assigned by the American Institute, and all material was kept in its original order. The material relates to the organizational preparations, financial data, and prize and entry information for the annual fairs. The bound volumes consist of Minute Books of various committees, Registers of Premiums, Entries, Judges, Invitations, and Tickets, and Account Books, Receipt Books, and Bank Books.
    There is little or no printed material regarding the fairs, and the correspondence relating to them is in the Administrative Subseries. The material in the Annual Fair Subseries contains the following main categories of information.
    Business and Financial - The foldered material contains files entitled "Vouchers" for almost every year that a fair was held. The files consist of bills and receipts for payment by the American Institute to individuals and companies that provided services for the fair. The services include construction, concession stands, cleaning, and advertising. In some cases, vouchers pertaining to expenses incurred by specific committees are identified by the names of those committees. For instance, specific folders might be labeled as the vouchers of the Printing and Publication Committee or the Arrangement Committee. Some financial information, specifically, accounts of receipts and expenditures of any given year's fair can also be found within the foldered Reports of the Board of Managers and Finance Committees.
    Many bound volumes also contain financial information. There are numerous Account Books, Receipt Books, and Bank Books (see container list for details).
    Reports and Minutes - The foldered material contains reports written by the various committees involved in the planning of the annual fairs. The reports and minutes of the Board of Managers detail the expenses and work of each individual committee. The nature of the reports of specific committees, such as the Ticket Committee, the Premium Committee, or the Finance Committee, is generally evident by the name of the committee.
    The bound volumes also contain information on the organizing committees. There are volumes of the Minutes of the Board of Managers for almost every year a fair was held. In addition to recording the minutes of the Board of Managers, the volumes contain lists of the members of each of the Fair's committees and record each committee's duties. The Minutes of the Board of Managers also detail the rules and regulations of the Fairs, payment of bills, and the votes on various motions. Minute books also exist for some of the committees for many of the fairs dated between 1840 and 1872. Some of the committees represented in these minute books are the Premium Committee, the Printing and Publication Committee, Committee of Arrangements, Finance Committee, Invitation Committee, Committee on Gas, Light, and Water, Floor Committee, Ticket Committee, Flag Committee, and the Committee on Audit.
    Exhibit Entries - There is very little information pertaining expressly to entrants in fairs that were held prior to 1890, but between the years 1890 and 1897, entry forms appear for each exhibitor. These entry forms provide detailed information on exhibitors and their products or inventions. The entry forms list the exhibitors' name and address, the article submitted, the name of the inventor and/or manufacturer, and sometimes provide a description of the exhibit.
    The bound Registers of Entries list the name of the entrant, the product or invention being entered, and the entrant's designated number. The registers can be cross-referenced with the "Judges Reports" to locate comments on specific entries.
    Judges - In the foldered material, information on judging at the annual fair can be found within the "Judges' Reports." These reports are extensive and cover the vast array of exhibits for almost every year of the Annual Fair. The Judges' Reports are forms in which judges, chosen by the Institute for their expertise in a given field, evaluate exhibits and select prize winners. The reports list entries according to exhibit number and do not identify the name of the person or company exhibiting the product.
    The bound volumes also include Registers of Judges for various years between 1842 and 1892. These registers list the judges selected for each department or group category by year. Because the Premium Committee selected the judges for each Fair, the Minute Books of the Premium Committees also provide information on the judges chosen for that particular year.
    Premiums - Not much information on premiums is found within the foldered material. Although the Judges' Reports identify the winners of the premiums, the Reports generally do not include lists of the winners. Similarly, the Premium Committee Reports often list a total number of premiums awarded but usually do not include names of specific winners. Only a small number of folders entitled "Medal Awards" that exist for certain years include receipts from winners of premiums for their awards.
    The bound volumes contain more material on the premiums awarded. The Registers of Premiums list the prizes awarded at each fair. They include the name of the premium winner, the winner's place of residence, the premium awarded, the category of the award, and sometimes, the winner's signature.
    Fair Attendance - Information on fair attendance can be found in the Reports of the Ticket Committees. Most of the reports provide the total number of tickets sold, as well as tickets issued at no charge to members, schools, and guests. Some years also include daily totals of tickets sold. Additionally, the Reports of the Board of Managers often remark on the attendance for an annual fair. Although the reports do not always provide detailed numbers, they will often comment on the attendance of the fair in comparison to last year's figures.
    The bound Registers of Invitations list people invited to the Annual Fairs. The invitations generally included government officials, members of the press, clergymen, and other significant people within New York society. Also included is the bound Members' Ticket Register from 1897, which lists the number of tickets given to each member of the American Institute, and the Minutes of the Invitation Committee from 1850 to 1852.